welcome to meditating with Chavo Ricky
I'm a cognitive psychologists and
cognitive scientists at the University
of Toronto academically teach and
scientifically study phenomena like
mindfulness Insight flow mystical
experience transformative experience
higher states of consciousness the
cultivation of wisdom the aspiration to
enlightenment in addition I've been
practicing the personal meditation met a
contemplation Tai Chi Chuan
and she come for over 29 years and
teaching them close to twenty years
professionally welcome you're joining us
for the first time please know that this
is a progressive course we have finished
the introductory course and now every
second Monday teaching more advanced
techniques that build on the practices
in the principles of the introductory
course and also build on each other and
progressive manner I would strongly
recommend that you go to the links in
the description of this video the
previous lessons work your ways through
catch up so that you can benefit both
from the teaching and from the community
because it assange it around this
practice is a wonderful sign of
wonderful community as I mentioned we
have a Dharma day every second Monday
and then we sit every day and we also
sit and do review on Tuesdays for Friday
every day has a question and answer at
the end please keep your q and a's for
today's but for the cure days at the end
of the Monday Friday sessions to the
psychology of practices that I'm
teaching you if you have more
encompassing questions please come to
the livestream Q&A and do every third
Friday which I believe is June 19th 3:00
p.m. Eastern Time
it would really help me to help others
if you would like the stream to increase
its visibility and the YouTube algorithm
and so what I would like to do is do one
more instance of review and enactment of
lectio Divina with you
today so what we'll do first because you
should always do this first before you
practice lectio divina is we should sit
we're going to have a shorter sit today
just 10 minutes so we have more time for
both enacting the Lexi Oh Davina and for
questions so please get yourself into
your basic posture set your phones I do
not disturb and we will begin when I say
again again
slowly come out of you practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice with your
everyday consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
all right
so let's do you lectio divina again I'll
quickly review the stages so you want
enacted engagement we're gonna recite
the texts we're going to set the
intention maybe a reverential reverence
what a for the revelation was going to
be revealed within a trust to
transformation we're not just reading
for information so we're setting our
minds for reverence and transformation
I'm going to recite it out loud now
we're going to move to the what what
what perhaps us what catches our
attention and there was a zero in the
recitation repeating that when we moved
to the embodied emotional associations
come up the thoughts what imagery
metaphorical literal can we enact
imaginably not in her head but is if we
were moving through the world embody the
motion until perspective a way of seeing
and being takes shape and then we moved
to the existential what would it be like
to live this way what would it be like
if this was my default mode of being if
you fall way of seeing none that moves
us to the ecstatic eternal what's being
disclosed about the world that I have
not seen or forgotten then what does the
demand for me in order to conform to
what what transformation do I need how
am I responsible to it how can I respond
to it by transforming myself I'm going
to depart slightly from the practice I'm
going to read the sacred poetry again
from Steven Mitchell and you should
always do poetry and prose
synth Amata and how they talk to each
other is an important way in which they
could talk to you but I thought for the
reading I want to do something a little
bit more challenging this is my third
time doing this and I wanted to pick up
on something that other people
Korean in particular it has been sort of
zeroing in on and this sucks the
practice into and so into a broader
context because I want to give you a
sense of how it this practice because as
I keep saying the touchstone for this is
how you notice it right impacting
impregnating you know transforming your
life so I picked up Spinoza
because he keeps coming up and I don't
think that's happen stance I recommended
a particular treatise to crema God
heaven sorry God humans in their
well-being so I'm just using this
particular because it's a nice little
book for caring around it's easily
available so what I want to do is I want
to first of all read the poetry or
through the practice with you then go
into the prose Spinoza's challenging
he's challenging in many ways he's
challenging because he's the one of the
most logically rigorous he's considered
the greatest of the rationalist
philosophers reading Spinoza's at time
worth reading and mathematical proof
she's challenging that way is also
challenging because he's right in the
heart of the Scientific Revolution and
he's doing something that's very very
interesting and many of you I suspect I
hope I hope you don't take this wrong I
hope you sir made me disagree a little
bit with it because you're going to
encounter in Lexi o things that you
don't initially agree with so there's
two things you can do and this is why
this is especially challenging one is
you can just get into argumentation with
with the philosopher he should do that
but I think the correct practice for
doing that is deal logos with somebody
else that's not so then what we have to
do is if we're not gonna specific these
are our
argue with the philosopher what does
Alexio davina mean for us in that
situation and what I'm going to try and
show you is it means I don't get
involved so much with the matter of what
the person is saying as the manner try
to try to you agree or disagree so much
with what Spinoza is saying as try to
get the try to see the perspective
adverbial what would it be like to see
the world the way Spinoza does such that
what he is saying makes sense and seems
plausible you still may reject it
of course I'm not here to you know
surreptitiously try to convince you of
things at least I hope not
if that secret of the genders at work
I'm calling on whatever resources in me
right now to challenge it and prevent it
from being dominant though what I want
to show you is very often and this is an
important point for do logos we can come
to learn and get a profound insight from
people even if we don't ultimately agree
with them so that's that's why I chose
this it's challenging in two ways
because you need to you need to read
people who are going to challenge you
not just in the positive sense of oh
that's wonderful I hadn't thought about
that before but also in the serve
negative fence oh that's difficult but I
hadn't thought of that before all right
so let's let's start let's start with
some poetry so this is from even foot
antivenom Evonik sorry sorry for the
mispronunciation Evonik who who is an
inuit shaman and she wrote in the mid
19th to early 20th century
so I'm setting myself here's my you know
my mentioned of these set these before
me as an act of setting my intention to
set myself for reverence set myself for
transformation the Great Sea has set me
in motion set me adrift moving like
moving me like a weed in a river the sky
and the strong wind have moved the
spirit inside me till I am carried away
trembling with joy
so what's calling me there is moving me
like a reed in a river moving me like to
read in a river I can I can feel what
it's like to be a you're like on a boat
mechanic client perhaps and the your
perception does that shift where you
feel the whole of the ocean moving
beneath you moving you and you feel like
a reed and a river
nothing damaged miss a service that you
feel this tremendous motion and it
resonates with her resonates it moves
her inside there's a responsiveness that
comes out there's something that that's
has an affinity to that outer emotion if
there's an inner outer motion I'm
sensing that affinity what would that be
like to move around the world sensing
that the ocean of being the way it's
moving around me but also through me and
not just through me like a 400 thing
that very movement within me is the
movement that is me what would it be
like to live from that perspective
what's being disclosed to me about the
world what call for transformation would
conform me to it how can I wake up to it
for more alive
on a full-blown insight just just a
sense for me today an inkling or what
that would mean how I could start living
this but I can only live it with a kind
of transformation so a tiny bit of
background for Spinoza for some of the
words he's going to use it's important
when you encounter people make them look
like I said make sure you've studied
this for information before you read it
for transformation when those is going
to use words here my God and nature and
idea we need something different than
those are normally mean we find about
nature he's talking about how things
moves through space he's talking about
causation and energy but we would now
call energy force the time of God he's
talking about the patterns that give
things their structural functional
organization make them one with
themselves and another sense one with
each other such that I can make sense of
them he's talking about intelligibility
he's talking about idea he's hung he's
not talking about just a thought in your
mind a representation he's talking about
that structural functional organization
that makes things knowable and then what
he says is it when he says he always
says God or nature is what he's trying
to do is he's trying
notice how we have traditionally put
these in opposition to each other are
that two worlds way of thinking there's
value to this two worlds way of thinking
paul van der clay was on my discord
server and there's a recording you can
go on youtube anew and mark from this
sangha asked him a question about that
and paul gave an excellent answer and
you should go and listen to that listen
to it carefully
counterbalance what's being said here
but nevertheless here what is being said
here as well because what Spinoza is
saying is what makes something act to be
the way it is and what makes it capable
of being understood are just two
different eyes like your left and right
field of field of vision and what your
brain does is it doesn't look at them
and oppose them it looks through them
and beyond them into their depth like
what we do in Praja so that's what
Spinoza is talking about that's what
he's trying to get us to see because he
sees that the Scientific Revolution
which is many people rightly criticized
for flattening the world getting rid of
the two worlds might also contain within
it a real spiritual potential which is
the spiritual potential of seeing this
seeing this deep depth ok so you've read
some information you've got an
informative understanding of Spinoza now
you set yourself for reverence and for
transformation it's a fairly long
reading in itself reason cannot fulfill
us and make us happy this is from one of
the probably the greatest rationalist of
all time what are you saying
therefore we must ask whether there is a
particular kind of knowledge by which we
could attain perfect happiness the kind
of knowledge that leads to happiness
does not come from a source that is
distinct from happiness to the mind as
the mind perceives happiness it becomes
united with it to put it another way the
knowledge of happiness evokes love for
happiness and turn for love of happiness
evokes love for its source which we call
God a God or nature God cannot reveal
himself directly to us but only through
his blessing and receiving his blessing
we become united with him in this union
does our blessedness our happiness
consist plus I do not say we must know
God as he is or even that we should
know him adequately it is sufficient to
know him to some degree in order to be
united with him even the knowledge we
have of our own bodies is very
particular we do not know our bodies
just as they are yet we are totally
united with our bodies the knowledge of
God is not the consequence of something
else but is immediate and direct
knowledge of God is the cause of all
other knowledge and so must be acquired
by itself alone moreover by our very
nature we are united with God so without
him we can neither exist nor be known
see that the union with that God is so
close that it is evident we cannot know
him
except directly the relationship of the
soul to the body and of the divine idea
to nature is one of the love you can
observe this union by observing
ourselves the feelings within the soul
are consistently finding expression and
the actions and the movements of the
body the union of the soul with the body
is one of total sympathy and when we
come fully aware of this union we may
truly say that we have been born again
see what he's doing he's moving between
religious and scientific language so I'm
picking up on that and what part of the
text is resonating with that last part
that last part really sings to me
because he's obviously alluding to
Christianity but he's doing something
with it there's even so he's
transforming something and that's
exemplifying the transformation that
he's calling to me with the union of the
soul with the body is one of total
sympathy and when we become fully aware
of this union we may truly say that we
have been born again sympathy here
doesn't mean feeling sorry for someone
it means being in total affinity total
attunement resonant at one
and when we true when we become one we
become fully aware of this union we may
truly say that we have been born again
they may be born again
anything waking up so the way the mind
and the body are united in a profound
kind of love not just that I have but a
love that makes me who I am I love I
participated is the same kind of love I
can have for God or nature they are the
same in some deep way one is a lived
metaphor for the other I can sense this
so I'm trying to enact it trying to
really enact it what does this mean so
what's coming up for Mina's emotional it
was when I'm moving in Tai Chi and the
distinction between mind and body and me
and world breaks down not into some
amorphous thing but into this like that
what he's saying this vibrant love this
sympathy sensing this I'm sensing the
Sun of that taking this as this is what
he's calling me to this is what he's
calling to me to he's trying to get me
to see that these two ways of seeing
that we normally opposed I can actually
see through them I can be born again I
can see through them
now I'm falling into a word of worthless
silence I'm just speaking to share with
you so getting a sense of what he needs
somehow beyond these write deeper than
this separations is that which makes
which grounds the things that have been
separated deeper than mind and body
deeper than self and world deeper than
God in nature all of these see what he's
doing I could feel it and feel it I
don't just mean like a feeling I mean
the texture and taste of my mind and the
way my energy is moving and the way my
body is coming alive to me the way the
world feels almost town tangible and
palpable to me it's like it's vibrating
they could have a sense an inkling of
what it is not to agree with Spinoza but
to see finis istic Lee to see the way
Spinoza song see what he's offering and
what he's afforded me now I feel the two
talking to each other it's abstract
scientific philosopher does he knew it
shaman and the see of being God or
nature and not the same tech not
different
I hope that was helpful to you so you've
had three different instances three
different tax three different this one
was more challenging I've tried to
demonstrate and exemplify to you what
Lex you're Davina is like notice what
you could then do this is something that
came up in my discussion this guy sends
talk it's going to come out in today's
Villalobos voices with Vicki how once
you've done the lectio on Spinoza you
still might have Mostafa chol
disagreements but now there is it now
your disagreement comes from a profound
place of understanding so that you have
hopefully respect to see things properly
SPECT lettuce to see the thing properly
you see it properly you have true
enacted respect and then you can enter
into deep dialo goes with Spinoza in a
disagreement and Lexia would plead in to
the logos alright thank you so much for
your patience it's it's helpful to have
a community that will listen and I thank
you for that question from Alex siminoff
on discord yeah discord discussion on
that as some people focus on feeling
emotions I focus on seeing more honest
of a person beyond the usual roles can
you clarify we aim to enhance cognitive
empathy seeing world from another
person's perspective or affective
empathy feeling exactly what they feel
are feeling good so I don't mean to just
riff on what just happened but you're
trying to do both because what the
cognitive science is showing is that
these two actually deeply interpenetrate
and mutually afford each other you want
both effective empathy and cognitive
empathy and you want and part of you
want to realize is in fact what I just
said are the interpenetrate and mutually
afford each other mark the foe is there
a prescribed
path for moving into novice then after
novice since reading disagreeable text
seems more advanced to me I would I yeah
it is more advanced it's more
challenging I I think you're making a
good point and I did hesitate about
doing today for the reason that you
mentioned
I wouldn't it making I wouldn't this is
how I would say it I think initially you
should read texts that more are more up
more agreeably let's put it that way
resonate with you preponderantly but
throw in because and it's for your
reading for example you're going through
Stephen Mitchell's anthology you gonna
encountering encounter things that
challenge you is he does that he's a
good teacher good teacher should it has
to find that balance between reaching
you and challenging you but I also
respect what you're saying mark and I
think it's a good idea if you're
starting to encounter a lot of texts
that are disagreeable to you in Alexio
davina that you know you have a place
where you can carry them in to do logos
other people who are willing perhaps to
engage with you in a way that is
continuous with not identical tilta to
but continuous with what's happening
with you and Alexia Davina it's a
difficult question to answer
precisely because unlike what might be
the case in a monastery so this is a
very practical but it's a very important
reason it's very plausible to for me to
assume that we have a very heterogeneous
mix of people in this segment and so I'm
trying to teach in a way that can and
that it's tricky and I know I don't
always get it right
I'm trying to teach in a way that's not
that sweet spot that I can call two
people or more novice but also challenge
people who moved beyond honest I hope
that answers your question
what I'm trying to say is I take
seriously what you're saying and I do
try to adjust my teaching not to it
Chris Hudson in my book of poetry hasn't
arrived from Amazon yet is it worth
trying Lexie Oh Davina with just the
prose yes it is continuity practice more
important than cognate quantity so try
it yeah try it you'll still get
something out of it and then what I hope
is when you start reading the poetry
first you'll get sort of a burst of
freshness in the synth Amata between the
poetry and the prose mark the fehb open
oh we've done that sorry Reynard Ludwig
oh this is the 300th question that I've
been asked is what I mean what an
amazing Sangha what an amazing Sangha is
it preferable for Luxio Divina to be
practiced on the meditation cushion I
find it easier to sit at my desk for the
reading this is where I do all my deep
thinking and contemplation it's as long
as the physical act of moving from your
pillow to where you want to sit doesn't
snug doesn't sort of snap you out of the
receptive state that you have cultivated
the the the that state that is very
sensitive towards insight and depth that
it doesn't snap you out of the receptive
state that you've cultivated in your
city so I can't tell that of you I don't
know you and what happens in that
situation so ask yourself am i carrying
it over am I still in the same place the
same process I was a moment ago when I
was sitting or does moving into this
familiar thing snapped me into a
different mode because that's also a
real possibility but if you can honestly
say there's like no no I feel the
continuity I feel that here the presence
that was in my practice is present here
on my desk that by all means do that if
you find that helpful and conducive I
hope you found today's lesson helpful
and conducive I want to thank you all
for joining and one is always to thank
my dear friend and techno mage Omar
behind the scenes my beloved son Jason
is always there in a pinch please
subscribe to this channel to be notified
of the next video you'll also find links
to the lecture series awakening for the
meeting crisis
you'll also find discussion series
voices with reveille key where all of
these issues and the wider context and
the significant depths of them are
explored and I hope developed in a way
that you'd find helpful and
transformative invite others who might
benefit from this practice by sharing
this series please I've just mentioned
it if you get a chance and brad is here
pleasure of doubt go on to the discord
server to chat with others I had the
great pleasure of listening
I stayed up too late to do it to paul
banach that he was on voices with her
baby with me and then he went on the
discord and answered questions and it
was it was beautiful and it was it was
it was enlivening it was challenging you
know I I'm Paul disagree but there was
that respect that I've been talking
about and I I think this is clear to me
now that what's forming on the discord
server is is just another kind of Sangha
in which this Sangha can sit properly
and be nourished and grow we're doing
this every weekday morning at 9:30 a.m.
Eastern Time please remember the
continuity practice is more important
than quantity of practice there's no
enemy worse than your own mind and body
there's no friend no Ally no companion
on the way better than your own mind and
body
he lamps unto yourself they carry one
I'll see you on Friday
I mean sorry I'll see you on Monday